<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ios | Fancy Pixel]]></title>
  <link href="http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/categories/ios/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fancypixel.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-21T09:34:10+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://fancypixel.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Fancy Pixel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playing with UIDynamics in iOS 9]]></title>
    <link href="http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/06/19/playing-with-uidynamics-in-ios-9/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-19T12:35:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/06/19/playing-with-uidynamics-in-ios-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>UIDynamics was a welcome addition to the iOS 7 SDK. It&rsquo;s basically a physics engine backing common UIViews, allowing us to define physics traits to the UI elements. The API is fairly straightforward, so you can easily create animations and transitions that look and feel great. I already covered the basics in <a href="http://andreamazz.github.io/blog/2014/05/22/uikit-dynamics/">this article</a> a while ago, this time we&rsquo;ll be looking at what&rsquo;s new in UIDynamics in iOS 9.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Collision Bounds</h2>

<p>The first release of UIDynamics shipped with a collision system (provided by <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/UIKit/Reference/UICollisionBehavior_Class/">UICollisionBehavior</a>) that only supported rectangular bodies. It made sense, since <code>UIView</code>s are backed by rectangular frames, but it&rsquo;s not uncommon to have a circular view, or even better our own custom Bezier path. With iOS 9 a new property has been added to the <code>UIDynamicItem</code> protocol: <code>UIDynamicItemCollisionBoundsType</code>, which accepts one of these enum values:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Rectangle</code></li>
<li><code>Ellipse</code></li>
<li><code>Path</code></li>
</ul>


<p>The property is readonly, so if we want to change it we need to provide our own subclass:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">class Ellipse: UIView {
  override var collisionBoundsType: UIDynamicItemCollisionBoundsType {
    return .Ellipse
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is a UIView with the default collision bound:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-06-19/slide.gif" width="500" title="&lsquo;Slide&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>This is the same UIView with the <code>.Ellipse</code>:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-06-19/roll.gif" width="500" title="&lsquo;Roll&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>This covers round views, if we want to get fancy and draw a more complex view with a coherent rigid body we can use the enum property <code>.Path</code> and also override this property:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">var collisionBoundingPath: UIBezierPath { get }
</code></pre>

<p>The path can be whatever you can think of, as long as it&rsquo;s convex (this means that for any given couple of points inside the polygon, the segment between the two is always entirely contained in the polygon itself) and counter-clockwise wound.<br/>
The convex requirement could be a significant limit, so <code>UIDynamicItemGroup</code> was introduced to specify shapes as a group of different shapes. This way as long as each shape in the group is convex we are fine even if the resulting polygon composition is concave.</p>

<h2>Field Behavior</h2>

<p>Field behaviors are a new type of behavior that is applied to the whole scene. The most common example that we&rsquo;ve been using implicitly all along is <code>UIGravityBehavior</code>, which applies a down force to each item in the scene. Now we can use a new set of field forces, like Radial (the forces are stronger at the center and weaker around the edges), Noise (forces with different magnitudes are scattered around the field), and so on.</p>

<h2>Dynamic Item Behavior</h2>

<p><code>UIDynamicItemBehavior</code> received a couple of interesting new properties:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">var charge: CGFloat
var anchored: Bool
</code></pre>

<p><code>charge</code> represent the <em>electric charge</em> that can influence how an item moves in an electric or magnetic field (yeah, it&rsquo;s bonkers), while <code>anchored</code> basically turns a shape into a static object that participates in the collisions, but without response (if something crashes into the item, it won&rsquo;t budge), so it&rsquo;s perfect to represent something like a floor or a wall.</p>

<h2>Attachment Behavior</h2>

<p><code>UIAttachmentBehavior</code> was revamped and now has a sleuth of new methods and properties, like <code>frictionTorque</code> and <code>attachmentRange</code>. The attachments can now be more flexible, we can specify relative sliding movements, fixed attachments, rope attachments and what I like the most: pin attachment. Think of two objects nailed together and you get the idea.</p>

<p>This more or less covers what&rsquo;s new in UIDynamics, now it&rsquo;s time to drop the changelog and start building something silly.</p>

<h1>Let&rsquo;s play ball</h1>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been spending a lot of idle time with <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ball-king/id946496840?mt=8">Ball King</a> in the last week. It&rsquo;s a brilliant little time waster, the concept is simple but well executed. Also it adopts the same monetization policies of the Apple design winner Crossy Road: it doesn&rsquo;t bother the player in any way. Kudos.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-06-19/ballking.jpeg" width="322" height="572" title="&lsquo;Ball King&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>One thing I really like about it is the physic model of the ball and how the hoop&rsquo;s backboard reacts when it gets hit by it. Looks like a fun exercise to test out the new UIDynamics stuff listed above. Let&rsquo;s take a step by step look at how to build our own scruffy version: <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/BallSwift">BallSwift</a></p>

<h2>The hoop</h2>

<p>The basket can be created with a single UIView acting as the backboard, a couple of views with rigid bodies as the left and right arms of the hoop, and a frontmost view as the hoop itself (without a physic body). Using the previously defined class <code>Ellipse</code> we can create the visual representation of our game scene:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">/* 
Build the hoop, setup the world appearance
*/
func buildViews() {
  board = UIView(frame: CGRect(x: hoopPosition.x, y: hoopPosition.y, width: 100, height: 100))
  board.backgroundColor = .whiteColor()
  board.layer.borderColor = UIColor(red: 0.98, green: 0.98, blue: 0.98, alpha: 1).CGColor
  board.layer.borderWidth = 2

  board.addSubview({
    let v = UIView(frame: CGRect(x: 30, y: 43, width: 40, height: 40))
    v.backgroundColor = .clearColor()
    v.layer.borderColor = UIColor(red: 0.4, green: 0.4, blue: 0.4, alpha: 1).CGColor
    v.layer.borderWidth = 5
    return v
    }())

  leftHoop = Ellipse(frame: CGRect(x: hoopPosition.x + 20, y: hoopPosition.y + 80, width: 10, height: 6))
  leftHoop.backgroundColor = .clearColor()
  leftHoop.layer.cornerRadius = 3

  rightHoop = Ellipse(frame: CGRect(x: hoopPosition.x + 70, y: hoopPosition.y + 80, width: 10, height: 6))
  rightHoop.backgroundColor = .clearColor()
  rightHoop.layer.cornerRadius = 3

  hoop = UIView(frame: CGRect(x: hoopPosition.x + 20, y: hoopPosition.y + 80, width: 60, height: 6))
  hoop.backgroundColor = UIColor(red: 177.0/255.0, green: 25.0/255.0, blue: 25.0/255.0, alpha: 1)
  hoop.layer.cornerRadius = 3

  [board, leftHoop, rightHoop, floor, ball, hoop].map({self.view.addSubview($0)})
}
</code></pre>

<p>Nothing new here, the hoop is created programmatically and is placed in the constant <code>CGPoint hoopPosition</code>. The order of the views is important though, since we want the hoop to be above the basket ball.</p>

<h2>Nuts and bolts</h2>

<p>The most important part of the hoop are the left and right <em>arms</em>. They need a physical round body (so that the collision with the ball is smooth) and need to be bolted to the board and the front hoop. These two will be basic <code>UIDynamicItem</code>s and won&rsquo;t partecipate directly in the collisions. The newly introduced pin attachment is perfect for this job, it can hold everything together quite nicely as we can see in this rather ugly drawing:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-06-19/hoop.png" width="600" height="400" title="&lsquo;Hoop&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The pin can be attached only to a couple of views at a time, within a given absolute spatial point:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">let bolts = [
  CGPoint(x: hoopPosition.x + 25, y: hoopPosition.y + 85), // leftHoop -&gt; Board
  CGPoint(x: hoopPosition.x + 75, y: hoopPosition.y + 85), // rightHoop -&gt; Board
  CGPoint(x: hoopPosition.x + 25, y: hoopPosition.y + 85), // hoop -&gt; Board (L)
  CGPoint(x: hoopPosition.x + 75, y: hoopPosition.y + 85)] // hoop -&gt; Board (R)

// Build the board
zip([leftHoop, rightHoop, hoop, hoop], offsets).map({
  (item, offset) in
  animator?.addBehavior(UIAttachmentBehavior.pinAttachmentWithItem(item, attachedToItem: board, attachmentAnchor: bolts))
})
</code></pre>

<p>If you&rsquo;re not participating in the race to Swift&rsquo;s functional awesomeness you&rsquo;re probably not familiar with zip and map. It might seem contrived at first, but it&rsquo;s rather simple: each view is coupled with the offset point in which we&rsquo;re going to pin the attachment, resulting in an array of tuples that is then used in the map function that, as the name suggests, creates a mapping with each element of the array with the provided closure. This results in both the left and right arms of the hoop to be bolted to the board and the front hoop as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Left arm bolted to the left of the board</li>
<li>Right arm bolted to the right of the board</li>
<li>Hoop bolted to the left of the board</li>
<li>Hoop bolted to the left of the board</li>
</ul>


<p>The next step requires us to <em>hang</em> the board, letting it rest loosely, so that a collision can cause it to swivel a bit like it does in Ball King:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">// Set the density of the hoop, and fix its angle
// Hang the hoop
animator?.addBehavior({
  let attachment = UIAttachmentBehavior(item: board, attachedToAnchor: CGPoint(x: hoopPosition.x, y: hoopPosition.y))
  attachment.length = 2
  attachment.damping = 5
  return attachment
  }())

animator?.addBehavior({
  let behavior = UIDynamicItemBehavior(items: [leftHoop, rightHoop])
  behavior.density = 10
  behavior.allowsRotation = false
  return behavior
  }())

// Block the board rotation
animator?.addBehavior({
  let behavior = UIDynamicItemBehavior(items: [board])
  behavior.allowsRotation = false
  return behavior
  }())
</code></pre>

<p>The hoop is ready to go. Let&rsquo;s take care of the ball, starting with a custom subclass of <code>UIImageView</code> with a rounded physics body, just like the <code>Ellipse</code> class:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">class Ball: UIImageView {
  override var collisionBoundsType: UIDynamicItemCollisionBoundsType {
    return .Ellipse
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>We can then istantiate the ball as a common UIImageView:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">let ball: Ball = {
  let ball = Ball(frame: CGRect(x: 0, y: 0, width: 28, height: 28))
  ball.image = UIImage(named: "ball")
  return ball
}()
</code></pre>

<p>Finally we set its physical properties:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">// Set the elasticity and density of the ball
animator?.addBehavior({
  let behavior = UIDynamicItemBehavior(items: [ball])
  behavior.elasticity = 1
  behavior.density = 3
  behavior.action = {
    if !CGRectIntersectsRect(self.ball.frame, self.view.frame) {
      self.setupBehaviors()
      self.ball.center = CGPoint(x: 40, y: self.view.frame.size.height - 100)
    }
  }
  return behavior
  }())
</code></pre>

<p>In this bit of code I set the elasticity (how much it should bounce after a collision), density (think of it as the <em>weight</em>) and a handy action closure that resets the world state when the ball exits the play area (the main view).</p>

<h2>Collisions and gravity</h2>

<p>I mentioned the new <code>anchored</code> property of <code>UIDynamicItemBehavior</code>, which disables the dynamic behavior of an object while keeping it in the collision&rsquo;s loop. Sounds like a great way to build a steady floor:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">// Anchor the floor
animator?.addBehavior({
  let behavior = UIDynamicItemBehavior(items: [floor])
  behavior.anchored = true
  return behavior
  }())
</code></pre>

<p>Forget to set this property and you&rsquo;ll be scratching your head a lot. I know I did.<br/>
Ok, everything is set, it just needs some gravity and a set of collisions:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">animator?.addBehavior(UICollisionBehavior(items: [leftHoop, rightHoop, floor, ball]))
animator?.addBehavior(UIGravityBehavior(items: [ball]))
</code></pre>

<p>The gravity is a field behavior that applies a down force of 1 point per second as default. The collision behavior takes as parameter only the views that should collide with each other. The world is set up, now we can apply an instantaneous force to the ball and keep our fingers crossed:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">let push = UIPushBehavior(items: [ball], mode: .Instantaneous)
push.angle = -1.35
push.magnitude = 1.56
animator?.addBehavior(push)
</code></pre>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-06-19/ball.gif" width="500" height="820" title="&lsquo;BallSwift&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>And there you go, it&rsquo;s really rough around the edges, but that was a lot of fun to build (yes, the clouds and the bushes are the same drawing, like in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ai7d1K4Yf6A">Super Mario</a>).<br/>
As always you can find the source on our <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/BallSwift">GitHub page</a>.</p>

<p>Until next time,</p>

<p>Andrea - <em><a href="https://twitter.com/theandreamazz">@theandreamazz</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iOS9 notifications and Text Input]]></title>
    <link href="http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/06/11/ios9-notifications-and-text-input/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-11T11:03:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/06/11/ios9-notifications-and-text-input</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When iOS8 opened the API to have actionable notifications many of us were disappointed that the text input action used in Messages wasn&rsquo;t available. It turns out that with iOS9 this API is now public, although as I&rsquo;m writing this the documentation doesn&rsquo;t mention it. After some digging in the UIKit changelog I was able to build a sample making use of this new behavior.<br/>
Like with iOS8 the NDA is more relaxed this year, but it still forbids showing screenshots. In any case, you&rsquo;ll find the full sample <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/text-notification-sample">on GitHub</a>.<br/>
Let&rsquo;s take a step by step look at what changed.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h1>Requesting the permission</h1>

<p>First of all we need to ask the permission to the user before we can start sending notifications. We start off by building a new <code>UIMutableUserNotificationAction</code>, that alongside the main properties of the notification will also specify the desired behavior:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">let textAction = UIMutableUserNotificationAction()
textAction.identifier = "TEXT_ACTION"
textAction.title = "Reply"
textAction.activationMode = .Background
textAction.authenticationRequired = false
textAction.destructive = false
textAction.behavior = .TextInput
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>behavior</code> property is a new addition of iOS9 and holds the <code>UIUserNotificationActionBehavior</code> enum:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">enum UIUserNotificationActionBehavior : UInt {
  case Default // the default action behavior
  case TextInput // system provided action behavior, allows text input from the user
}
</code></pre>

<p>With that out of the way the rest of the configuration didn&rsquo;t change much from iOS8:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">let category = UIMutableUserNotificationCategory()
category.identifier = "CATEGORY_ID"
category.setActions([textAction], forContext: .Default)
category.setActions([textAction], forContext: .Minimal)

let categories = NSSet(object: category) as! Set&lt;UIUserNotificationCategory&gt;
let settings = UIUserNotificationSettings(forTypes: [.Alert, .Badge, .Sound], categories: categories)
UIApplication.sharedApplication().registerUserNotificationSettings(settings)
</code></pre>

<p>One minor difference here is due to the new Swift 2 syntax, instead of:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">UIUserNotificationType.Alert | UIUserNotificationType.Sound | UIUserNotificationType.Badge
</code></pre>

<p>we need to use the much nicer</p>

<pre><code class="swift">[.Alert, .Sound, .Badge]
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s it, once the user grants the permission we can schedule a new local notification to test this out:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">static func scheduleNotification() {
    let now: NSDateComponents = NSCalendar.currentCalendar().components([.Hour, .Minute], fromDate: NSDate())

    let cal = NSCalendar(calendarIdentifier: NSCalendarIdentifierGregorian)!
    let date = cal.dateBySettingHour(now.hour, minute: now.minute + 1, second: 0, ofDate: NSDate(), options: NSCalendarOptions())
    let reminder = UILocalNotification()
    reminder.fireDate = date
    reminder.alertBody = "You can now reply with text"
    reminder.alertAction = "Cool"
    reminder.soundName = "sound.aif"
    reminder.category = "CATEGORY_ID"

    UIApplication.sharedApplication().scheduleLocalNotification(reminder)

    print("Firing at \(now.hour):\(now.minute+1)")
}
</code></pre>

<h1>Receiving the response</h1>

<p>Once the user activates the action and writes the reply our <code>AppDelegate</code> is called, receiving a new delegate message introduced in iOS9:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">func application(application: UIApplication, handleActionWithIdentifier identifier: String?, forLocalNotification notification: UILocalNotification, withResponseInfo responseInfo: [NSObject : AnyObject], completionHandler: () -&gt; Void) {
</code></pre>

<p>The text is stored in the <code>responseInfo</code> under the <code>UIUserNotificationActionResponseTypedTextKey</code> key:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">let reply = responseInfo[UIUserNotificationActionResponseTypedTextKey]
</code></pre>

<p>And that&rsquo;s it. A welcome addition to the API, let&rsquo;s hope that all the major messaging apps will adopt it soon.<br/>
You can find the full sample <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/text-notification-sample">here</a>. Once you run the app and schedule the notification, hop back to the home screen and you&rsquo;ll be able to reply with some text, that will be displayed in the app&rsquo;s view controller.</p>

<p>Until next time.<br/>
Andrea - <a href="https://twitter.com/theandreamazz">@theandreamazz</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gulps: new open source WatchKit app]]></title>
    <link href="http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/04/13/gulps-new-open-source-watchkit-app/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-13T21:26:20+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/04/13/gulps-new-open-source-watchkit-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We released a new app on the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gulps/id979057304?ls=1&amp;mt=8">AppStore</a> and decided to open source it. The app is called Gulps, a simple tracker of your daily water consumption. Gulps was a fun little side project built to learn a bit more about WatchKit and to strengthen my Swift-fu.<br/>
If you read our latest post on <a href="http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/03/29/share-data-between-watchkit-and-your-app-with-realm/">how to share data with Realm</a>, you&rsquo;ll find a lot of code in common in this app, but there&rsquo;s also quite a bit of new stuff that&rsquo;s worth checking out. For starters I personally really like the water meter that follows your device movement, made possible by the amazing <a href="https://github.com/dulaccc/DPMeterView">DPMeterView</a>. You might also like the Facebook Paper-like wavy effect in the onboarding, provided by one of my pride and joys, <a href="https://github.com/andreamazz/AMWaveTransition">AMWaveTransition</a>.<br/>
You&rsquo;ll find the source <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/gulps">here</a>.</p>

<p>Let us know what you think.<br/>
Until next time.</p>

<p>Andrea - <a href="https://twitter.com/theandreamazz">@theandreamazz</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Share data between WatchKit and your app with Realm]]></title>
    <link href="http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/03/29/share-data-between-watchkit-and-your-app-with-realm/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-29T15:00:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2015/03/29/share-data-between-watchkit-and-your-app-with-realm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a busy year for iOS developers. We got a slew of new toys to play with: a new version of iOS, new frameworks, a new language, new screen sizes and some new hardware to put on our wrists, just as soon as we thought that watches were anachronistic.<br/>
New technology is always exciting, but keeping up to date can be a daunting task when deadlines keep getting closer. Lately I&rsquo;ve been taking some time off to delve deeper in these new topics and build a simple app out of it (that we are planning to open source). At the time of this writeup the app is still waiting to be reviewed, so we&rsquo;re going to just focus on something that I learned in the process and that can be useful to a lot of other iOS devs: sharing data between your app and its WatchKit extension, using <a href="http://realm.io/">Realm</a>.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h1>Why Realm</h1>

<p>Realm is a great replacement for both SQLite and Core Data, it offers a quick and painless way to persist data in your iOS (and Android) app. The thing that makes it so great is the ease of use, it reduces your boilerplate code to next to nothing (I&rsquo;m watching you, Core Data), keeping things at a high level of abstraction (I&rsquo;m watching you SQLite) and&hellip; it&rsquo;s fast. It really is a brilliant piece of software, and I urge you to checkout the <a href="http://realm.io/docs/cocoa/0.91.1/">official documentation</a> if you&rsquo;re in need of a persistence framework for your app.</p>

<h1>The sample app</h1>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to learn how to share data between an app and its WatchKit extension, and what better way to use a sample app as reference?.
I&rsquo;m not a fan of TODO app demos, they always feel&hellip; unimaginative&hellip; but I have to admit that they are the perfect sample for a task like this. So, bear with me, let me introduce to you another TODO sample app: <em>Done!</em>, a simple TODO list where we can add items and mark them as done from our Apple Watch.</p>

<h1>Setting up Realm</h1>

<p>WatchKit extensions are just another target inside your app, just like Today extensions, so they are packed alongside your app, but they have their own life, and most importantly, their own bundle identifier. This means that data stored within an app is not visible to the extension and vice versa. Apple offers a way to solve the issue through app groups.<br/>
App groups, like bundle identifiers, are defined by a reverse URI and they are prefixed with <code>group.</code>. They let you share data between your apps and are tightly bound to your provisioning profile (luckily Xcode handles their creation in your developer portal with ease).<br/>
We can take advantage of that to create our Realm database in a shared space that will be visible (and writeable) by both our app and the app&rsquo;s WatchKit extension. Let&rsquo;s start by creating the group in our project&rsquo;s capabilities section:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-03-29/appgroup.png" width="640" height="150" title="&lsquo;App groups&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Once this is out of the way we can tell Realm to store the database inside the group.
We&rsquo;ll do so in our AppDelegate&rsquo;s <code>application(application: didFinishLaunchingWithOptions launchOptions:)</code> function:</p>

<pre><code>let directory: NSURL = NSFileManager.defaultManager().containerURLForSecurityApplicationGroupIdentifier("group.it.fancypixel.Done")!
let realmPath = directory.path!.stringByAppendingPathComponent("db.realm")
RLMRealm.setDefaultRealmPath(realmPath)
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s it, Realm is ready to go, we just need to define a model to persist. Let&rsquo;s do it:</p>

<pre><code>// Entry.swift
import Realm

class Entry: RLMObject {
  dynamic var title = ""
  dynamic var completed = false
}
</code></pre>

<h1>ViewController</h1>

<p>The ViewController handling the TODO list will be rather simple, it&rsquo;ll hold a plain <code>UITableView</code> with a custom header presenting the <code>UITextField</code> for the user&rsquo;s input, nothing fancy:</p>

<pre><code>// ViewController.swift
import Realm
import UIKit

class ViewController: UIViewController, UITableViewDelegate, UITableViewDataSource, UITextFieldDelegate {

    @IBOutlet var tableView: UITableView!
    var dataSource: RLMResults!

    override func viewDidLoad() {
        super.viewDidLoad()
        reloadEntries()
    }

    func tableView(tableView: UITableView, viewForHeaderInSection section: Int) -&gt; UIView? {
        let container = UIView(frame: CGRectMake(0, 0, self.view.frame.size.width, 60))
        let textField = UITextField(frame: CGRectMake(10, 10, self.view.frame.size.width - 20, 40))
        textField.delegate = self
        textField.textColor = UIColor.whiteColor()
        let placeholer = NSAttributedString(string: "Add an item", attributes: [NSForegroundColorAttributeName: UIColor.lightGrayColor()])
        textField.attributedPlaceholder = placeholer
        container.addSubview(textField)
        return container
    }

    func reloadEntries() {
        dataSource = Entry.allObjects()
        self.tableView.reloadData()
    }

    func textFieldShouldReturn(textField: UITextField) -&gt; Bool {
        textField.resignFirstResponder()

        let realm = RLMRealm.defaultRealm()
        realm.beginWriteTransaction()
        let entry = Entry()
        entry.title = textField.text
        entry.completed = false
        realm.addObject(entry)
        realm.commitWriteTransaction()
        reloadEntries()
        return true
    }

    func tableView(tableView: UITableView, numberOfRowsInSection section: Int) -&gt; Int {
        return Int(dataSource.count)
    }

    func tableView(tableView: UITableView, cellForRowAtIndexPath indexPath: NSIndexPath) -&gt; UITableViewCell {
        var cell = tableView.dequeueReusableCellWithIdentifier("Cell") as UITableViewCell
        let entry = dataSource[UInt(indexPath.row)] as Entry
        cell.textLabel!.text = entry.title
        cell.accessoryType = entry.completed ? .Checkmark : .None
        return cell
    }

    func tableView(tableView: UITableView, didSelectRowAtIndexPath indexPath: NSIndexPath) {
        let entry = dataSource[UInt(indexPath.row)] as Entry
        let realm = RLMRealm.defaultRealm()
        realm.beginWriteTransaction()
        entry.completed = !entry.completed
        realm.commitWriteTransaction()
        reloadEntries()
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see we are retrieving the table view&rsquo;s items from Realm with a simple call:</p>

<pre><code>Entry.allObjects()
</code></pre>

<p>and storing the changes with a couple of lines:</p>

<pre><code>realm.beginWriteTransaction()
let entry = Entry
entry.title = textField.text
entry.completed = false
realm.addObject(entry)
realm.commitWriteTransaction()
</code></pre>

<p>If you worked with Core Data in the past you should have a better understanding of my claim <em>&ldquo;less boilerplate code&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<h1>WatchKit</h1>

<p>Ok, new technology, new framework, so much to learn, right?<br/>
Well, it turns out that Apple did some thinking on this, and for what I witnessed, developing a Watch app is going to feel familiar for a lot of Cocoa and Cocoa Touch developers, albeit with some significant philosophical changes. First things first, let&rsquo;s create a new target holding the Watch app:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-03-29/newtarget.png" width="640" height="340" title="&lsquo;WatchKit target&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Then, the layout. We won&rsquo;t be using Autolayout, but something reminiscing a simplified version of Android&rsquo;s linear and relative layouts (no need to touch beefy XML files though, storyboards are still there for us). The layout for this will be a <code>WKInterfaceTable</code> with a custom <code>TableRowController</code>, holding a <code>WKInterfaceImage</code> and a <code>WKInterfaceLabel</code>:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-03-29/storyboard.png" width="600" height="260" title="&lsquo;WatchKit storyboard&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The custom <code>TableRowController</code> is a plain class with a couple of properties, so let&rsquo;s take a look at this first:</p>

<pre><code>class EntryTableRowController: NSObject {
    @IBOutlet var imageCheck: WKInterfaceImage!
    @IBOutlet var textLabel: WKInterfaceLabel!
}
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty straightforward, think of it as the equivalent of a custom <code>UITableViewCell</code>.<br/>
Let&rsquo;s take a look on how to populate the table:</p>

<pre><code>override func awakeWithContext(context: AnyObject?) {
    super.awakeWithContext(context)

    let directory: NSURL = NSFileManager.defaultManager().containerURLForSecurityApplicationGroupIdentifier("group.it.fancypixel.Done")!
    let realmPath = directory.path!.stringByAppendingPathComponent("db.realm")
    RLMRealm.setDefaultRealmPath(realmPath)
    reloadTableData()
}

func reloadTableData() {
    let realm = RLMRealm.defaultRealm()
    let dataSource = Entry.allObjects()

    watchTable.setNumberOfRows(Int(dataSource.count), withRowType: "EntryRow")

    for index in 0..&lt;Int(dataSource.count) {
        let entry = dataSource[UInt(index)] as Entry
        if let row = watchTable.rowControllerAtIndex(index) as? EntryTableRowController {
            row.textLabel.setText(entry.title)
            let imageName = entry.completed ? "check-completed" : "check-empty"
            row.imageCheck.setImageNamed(imageName)
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s a little different from what we&rsquo;re used in UIKit. No <code>delegate</code> nor <code>dataSource</code>, in WatchKit we explicitly define every row before showing the table.<br/>
Also, as you can see in the <code>awakeWithContext</code> function, we are setting up Realm as we did in the main app. As a side note, the pieces of code that are shared between the two targets (in our case, everything concerning the model) should be moved in a custom framework to avoid code duplication. For the purpose of this sample I opted to duplicate the Realm initialization and shared the model between the two targets, but in a more structured app I would definitely take the framework route.
If we build and run we can add an item on the phone, and once we reload the app we&rsquo;ll see the same item in the watch extension too.<br/>
That doesn&rsquo;t feel very responsive though, right? We&rsquo;ll fix that in a bit, but first let&rsquo;s add the ability to mark an item as <em>done</em> from the watch:</p>

<pre><code class="">override func table(table: WKInterfaceTable, didSelectRowAtIndex rowIndex: Int) {
    let dataSource = Entry.allObjects()
    let entry = dataSource[UInt(rowIndex)] as Entry
    let realm = RLMRealm.defaultRealm()
    realm.beginWriteTransaction()
    entry.completed = !entry.completed
    realm.commitWriteTransaction()
    reloadTableData()
}
</code></pre>

<p>That pretty much covers it. Right now it&rsquo;s even more apparent that even if the two apps are communicating, there&rsquo;s no real sense of interaction, since we need to reload the app to see the changes.</p>

<h1>Syncing data</h1>

<p>We need to somehow advertise that our watch app or our main app performed something meaningful. There are <em>official</em> ways to do that, and you can read more about them on <a href="http://natashatherobot.com/watchkit-open-ios-app-from-watch/">this blog post from Natasha The Robot</a>, but in this case I want to show you how a brilliant library called <a href="https://github.com/mutualmobile/MMWormhole">MMWormHole</a> can abstract this task for us.</p>

<h2>MMWormHole</h2>

<p>MMWormhole creates a bridge between an app and its extensions. The API is clear and concise and it has a delightfully geeky name. It works like a pub/sub system, one end registers its interest for a kind of message (defined by a string identifier), and the other end can broadcast a new event. When the event is raised the subscriber&rsquo;s handler is fired. Sounds like something we can leverage from our app. Let&rsquo;s start by registering interest in <code>watch</code> updates on our main app:</p>

<pre><code>self.wormhole.listenForMessageWithIdentifier("watchUpdate", listener: { (_) -&gt; Void in
    self.reloadEntries()
})
</code></pre>

<p>and on our watch app we&rsquo;ll listen for <code>main</code> updates:</p>

<pre><code>self.wormhole.listenForMessageWithIdentifier("mainUpdate", listener: { (_) -&gt; Void in
    self.reloadTableData()
})
</code></pre>

<p>And that&rsquo;s it. When something changes in our model we just need to call these function:</p>

<pre><code>// From the watch
self.wormhole.passMessageObject("update", identifier: "watchUpdate")

// From the main app
self.wormhole.passMessageObject(someObject, identifier: "mainUpdate")
</code></pre>

<h1>Realm notifications</h1>

<p><em>Update</em></p>

<p>Once this post was live, Tim Anglade from Realm reached out to me and was kind enough to point out that there&rsquo;s a built-in notification system in Realm, so MMWormHole in this case isn&rsquo;t really needed. The API is really easy to use and requires no configuration, here&rsquo;s how it works:</p>

<pre><code>realmToken = RLMRealm.defaultRealm().addNotificationBlock { note, realm in
    self.reloadEntries()
}
</code></pre>

<p>As long as we keep a strong pointer to the token, the system fires the notification block as soon as a write transaction is committed. You can find the updated code in the sample app.</p>

<h2>Demo</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the demo app in all of its glory:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-03-29/screenshot.gif" width="600" title="&lsquo;Done&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>As you can see it&rsquo;s really easy to bootstrap a simple app for WatchKit, and thanks to a couple of great open source libraries adding persistence and interactivity is a painless effort. A big <em>thank you</em> to both the Realm team and Mutual Mobile for the amazing work on MMWormHole.</p>

<p>As usual, you&rsquo;ll find the source code of the demo app on our <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/done-swift">GitHub page</a>. Feel free to leave a comment, we&rsquo;d love to hear your feedback.</p>

<p>Until next time,</p>

<p>Andrea - <em><a href="https://twitter.com/theandreamazz">@theandreamazz</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun with iBeacon]]></title>
    <link href="http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2014/07/01/fun-with-ibeacon/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-01T20:47:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fancypixel.github.io/blog/2014/07/01/fun-with-ibeacon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You probably know already what <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/userexperience/conceptual/LocationAwarenessPG/RegionMonitoring/RegionMonitoring.html">iBeacon</a> is, but just to reiterate, iBeacon is the Apple way of saying Bluetooth 4 Low Energy. At the cost of sounding like a mindless drone, by &lsquo;the Apple way of&rsquo; I mean &lsquo;it just works and shows a lot of potential&rsquo;. An iBeacon is a simple B4LE device that keeps broadcasting its presence. Other B4LE devices can sense when they reach the beacon without draining the battery (hence the LE) and making the user scream in agony. &ldquo;Oook, what do I do with it?&rdquo;. The best thing you can do is locating a user without the GPS, which means locating a user inside a building. The cool thing is that it&rsquo;s fast, it takes seconds to detect a beacon and to react to its vicinity (or lack there of), and it works within the reach of Bluetooth technology (let&rsquo;s say around a 50 meters radius). I should also mention that it works fine with Android too.</p>

<p>This week an <a href="http://estimote.com">Estimote</a> developer kit arrived in our offices, so we took the chance to play around with it.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>I already tried my hand with iBeacons in the not so distant past. Using <a href="https://github.com/lgaches/BeaconEmitter">BeaconEmitter</a> you can easily turn your Mac into a beacon, with no extra hardware required. When I experimented with iBeacons I had a couple of ideas on my mind, that involved being able to send a local notification to the user that enters in range of a device acting as a beacon. My dreams were crushed by the limits of the iOS 7.0 implementation, as I found out that:</p>

<ul>
<li>you can&rsquo;t react when the user&rsquo;s screen is turned off</li>
<li>you can&rsquo;t perform any action when your app is in background, even if you request the <code>location</code> background state</li>
<li>detecting when the user leaves a region takes quite a lot of time (at least 10/15 minutes)</li>
</ul>


<p>The most exciting thing about playing around with the Estimote SDK, besides the nifty packaging and well designed piece of hardware, is that my devices now have iOS 7.1. It turns out that with version 7.1, iOS is way more flexible and it&rsquo;s taking care of all the problems I faced with 7.0:</p>

<ul>
<li>you can show a local notification when the screen is off</li>
<li>you can perform operations when the user enters a region (even if the app was killed)</li>
<li>it takes second to detect when the user is out of range</li>
</ul>


<p>This turns everything around, iBeacons aren&rsquo;t just a gimmick now, but an exciting tool to experiment with.</p>

<h2>Building a sample</h2>

<p>First thing that came to our mind was to build a simple system to automatically check people in and out of the office. Really, as simple as it gets, it took a couple of hours to build, but it works surprisingly well.</p>

<h3>Rails backend</h3>

<p>To check people in and out we need a backend and an authentication system. Rails makes it easy, a model, a basic API and the help of Devise for the authentication process.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby"># app/model/checkin.rb lang:ruby
class Checkin &lt; ActiveRecord::Base

  belongs_to :user  
  enum direction: { in: 0, out: 1 }

end
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s a pretty basic model, taking advantage of Rails 4.1 enums.</p>

<p>The routes are scoped as APIs, just to be fancy:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby"># config/routes.rb
namespace :api, defaults: {format: :json} do
  namespace :v1 do
    post 'checkin', to: 'checkins#checkin'
    post 'checkout', to: 'checkins#checkout'
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>And the controller does pretty much just this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby"># checkins_controller.rb
def checkin
  checkin = Checkin.new(user: current_user, direction: :in)
  if checkin.save
    head :no_content
  else
    render json: {errors: checkin.errors}, status: :unprocessable_entity
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>The authentication is handled by Devise, and for simplicity we opted for HTTP Basic Authentication.</p>

<h3>iOS Client</h3>

<p>The iOS app needs to look for our trusty beacon, and once the user is in range of our region, it needs to make a POST call to our API. When the user walks out of the office the phone needs to do the same to the checkout API. The iOS APIs for handling beacons are inside CoreLocation, in this sample I&rsquo;ll be using two main delegate methods:</p>

<pre><code class="objectivec">- (void)locationManager:(CLLocationManager *)manager didEnterRegion:(CLRegion *)region;
- (void)locationManager:(CLLocationManager *)manager didExitRegion:(CLRegion *)region;
</code></pre>

<p>The good guy calling these two methods is a <code>CLLocationManager</code> instance. The location manager needs an instance of <code>CLBeaconRegion</code> to start doing its magic though. We can define a region by specifying a UUDID, an identifier, a major and a minor. It might sound confusing at first, but all those things boil down to this:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>UUDID</code>: A unique identifier of our beacon network. It&rsquo;s best practice to have one UUDID per App. Each beacon will share the same UUDID.</li>
<li><code>identifier</code>: It&rsquo;s a string representation of our network. It usually is the reverse URI of our App, something along the line of com.something.awesome.</li>
<li><code>major</code>: It&rsquo;s an integer that specifies the major group of our beacons. Think of it as a common number that can identify a bunch of beacons inside a building.</li>
<li><code>minor</code>: It&rsquo;s an integer that specifies the single beacon inside of a major group.</li>
</ul>


<p>So our basic config would be one UUDID and identifier per App, one major per building, and one minor per beacon. For the purposes of this sample we only have a beacon, so we can either disregard this info, or just specify whatever major and minor that we want, as long as it matches the ones configured in the beacon itself.
Now that all that is out of the way, let&rsquo;s get to the code:</p>

<pre><code class="objectivec">- (CLBeaconRegion *)region
{
    if (_region == nil) {
        NSUUID *proximityUUID = [[NSUUID alloc] initWithUUIDString:self.settings[@"udid"]];
        _region = [[CLBeaconRegion alloc] initWithProximityUUID:proximityUUID
                                                          major:[self.settings[@"major"] intValue]
                                                          minor:[self.settings[@"minor"] intValue]
                                                     identifier:self.settings[@"identifier"]];

        [_region setNotifyOnExit:YES];
        [_region setNotifyOnEntry:YES];
        [_region setNotifyEntryStateOnDisplay:YES];
    }
    return _region;
}
</code></pre>

<p>There we go, our lazy loaded region that reads the parameters from an NSDictionary. Cool, let&rsquo;s start monitoring:</p>

<pre><code class="objectivec">[self.manager startMonitoringForRegion:self.region];
[self.manager stopRangingBeaconsInRegion:self.region];  
</code></pre>

<p>The first line is pretty self explanatory, the second one just tells the system that I don&rsquo;t really care for the single beacons, I just need the region updates.</p>

<p>Now that we are monitoring the region, we just need to decide what to do when we are in and out of range:</p>

<pre><code class="objectivec">- (void)locationManager:(CLLocationManager *)manager didEnterRegion:(CLRegion *)region
{
    if ([region isKindOfClass:[CLBeaconRegion class]]) {
        CLBeaconRegion *beaconRegion = (CLBeaconRegion *)region;
        if ([beaconRegion.identifier isEqualToString:self.settings[@"identifier"]] &amp;&amp; [beaconRegion.major intValue] == [self.settings[@"major"] intValue] &amp;&amp; [beaconRegion.minor intValue]== [self.settings[@"minor"] intValue]) {
            UILocalNotification *notification = [[UILocalNotification alloc] init];
            notification.userInfo = @{@"identifier": region.identifier};
            notification.alertBody = [NSString stringWithFormat:@"Entering %@", region.identifier];
            notification.soundName = @"Default";
            [[UIApplication sharedApplication] presentLocalNotificationNow:notification];
            [self remoteCheckin:FPCheckDirectionIn];
        }
    }
}

- (void)locationManager:(CLLocationManager *)manager didExitRegion:(CLRegion *)region
{
    if ([region isKindOfClass:[CLBeaconRegion class]]) {
        CLBeaconRegion *beaconRegion = (CLBeaconRegion *)region;
        if ([beaconRegion.identifier isEqualToString:self.settings[@"identifier"]] &amp;&amp; [beaconRegion.major intValue] == [self.settings[@"major"] intValue] &amp;&amp; [beaconRegion.minor intValue]== [self.settings[@"minor"] intValue]) {
            UILocalNotification *notification = [[UILocalNotification alloc] init];
            notification.userInfo = @{@"identifier": region.identifier};
            notification.alertBody = [NSString stringWithFormat:@"Exiting %@", region.identifier];
            notification.soundName = @"Default";
            [[UIApplication sharedApplication] presentLocalNotificationNow:notification];
            [self remoteCheckin:FPCheckDirectionOut];
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we&rsquo;re just checking against our beacon, when we are in range or when we get out of range, we push a local notification and we perform a remote call to our Rails backend. You can find the full source on our Github account, don&rsquo;t worry.</p>

<h2>Who&rsquo;s Fancy?</h2>

<p>And there we go, the iOS app:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2014-07-01/iOS.png" title="&lsquo;Who&rsquo;s Fancy iOS&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>and the web page:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2014-07-01/rails.png" title="&lsquo;Who&rsquo;s Fancy Rails&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>You can find the rails and iOS code <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/whosfancy-rails">here</a> and <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/whosfancy-ios">here</a>.</p>

<h4>Android version</h4>

<p>We also pushed the Android version on our Github page, you can find it <a href="https://github.com/FancyPixel/whosfancy-android">here</a>.</p>

<p>Until next time.</p>

<p>Andrea</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
